<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Julia Evans]]></title>
  <link href="http://jvns.ca/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://jvns.ca/categories/opensource/atom/index.xml"/>
  <updated>0001-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jvns.ca</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Julia Evans]]></name>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning at open source sprints (no preparation required)]]></title>
    <link href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2015/04/12/learning-at-open-source-sprints/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-12T08:24:15+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://jvns.ca/blog/2015/04/12/learning-at-open-source-sprints/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m someone who isn&rsquo;t heavily involved in contributing code to OSS, and
normally go to sprints just to learn something new, and not with any
particular goals. This has never worked out that well for me, but I had
a new idea yesterday! Maybe if you&rsquo;re like me it will help you.</p>

<p>I was talking to someone yesterday about contributing to a relatively
complicated open source project during the sprints. And we worked out
that they were super super interested in learning about the project&rsquo;s
internals, and didn&rsquo;t necessarily need to contribute to the project!</p>

<p>Contributing to a project for the first time is hard. There&rsquo;s a lot
you need to know! And the area of the project you&rsquo;re interested in might
not necessarily need contributions right now! Or you might not be able
to make the contribution you&rsquo;re interested in on your first 3 days.</p>

<p>So we came up with an AWESOME IDEA. Instead of trying to write a
contribution, change the goals! The next time I go to a sprint, I think
I&rsquo;ll just</p>

<ol>
<li>pick a project I&rsquo;m interested in</li>
<li>decide on a thing I&rsquo;d like to learn about that project</li>
<li>start digging into the project, running code, and learn about that
thing</li>
<li>not worry about contributing</li>
</ol>

<p>For me, I think this could be way more fun and that I&rsquo;d learn a lot
more. And it would be fun to do this stuff near the team who works on
the project, regardless of whether or not they have time to help me :)</p>

<p>And maybe, while exploring with no particular goal, I&rsquo;d find a change
that needs making! :) Or if I wanted to contribute to the project 6
months down the road, I&rsquo;d be a little more prepared to do that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don&#39;t feel guilty about not contributing to open source]]></title>
    <link href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2014/04/26/i-dont-feel-guilty-about-not-contributing-to-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-26T08:56:33+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://jvns.ca/blog/2014/04/26/i-dont-feel-guilty-about-not-contributing-to-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a long time I had a vague feeling that I <em>should</em> be contributing
to open source more, and that it was in some way a Good Thing. And I
felt a little bit guilty about not doing it enough.</p>

<p>I used to have this dialog with myself pretty often:</p>

<ul>
<li>Okay, Julia, open source is good!</li>
<li>Yeah, I should go do some open source</li>
<li>What project? I don&rsquo;t know. huh.</li>
<li>I use <a href="https://www.pidgin.im/">Pidgin</a>! Maybe that</li>
<li><em>go look at pidgin</em></li>
<li>so many issues! I don&rsquo;t even know where to start</li>
<li>and it&rsquo;s in C! so many code! how do I even!</li>
<li>Give up, feel vaguely guilty</li>
</ul>

<p></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m trying to stop feeling guilty. Now if I&rsquo;m going to contribute to a
project, it needs to be something that I&rsquo;m motivated to do.
<a href="http://blog.melchua.com/">Mel Chua</a> gave a great talk at Hacker
School where she said motivation is made up of <em>competence</em> (I know
how to do this!), <em>autonomy</em> (I can make my own decisions!), and
<em>relatedness</em> (I know why I&rsquo;m doing this!).</p>

<p>In open source there&rsquo;s pretty high autonomy &ndash; nobody&rsquo;s ever going to
force you to work on anything. So what&rsquo;s usually missing is
<em>relatedness</em> and <em>competence</em>.</p>

<p>For relatedness, I&rsquo;ll ask myself:</p>

<p><strong>&ldquo;What do I hope to get out of contributing to this project?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>I want to know how it works! (contributing to Linux could be super
fun for this reason! Operating systems are amazing! My
<a href="https://github.com/jvns/gzip.jl">gunzip in julia</a> is a project
where I learned a ton.)</li>
<li>I found a bug and I want to fix it! I want to add a feature!</li>
<li>I want to build up a portfolio of programming work to get better
jobs!</li>
<li>I think this project is doing important work and I&rsquo;d like to advance
it! (Kelsey Gilmore-Innis&rsquo;s work on the
<a href="http://antievictionmappingproject.net/">Anti-Eviction Mapping Project</a>
is a great example)</li>
<li>I like spending time with the people who work on this project! (When
I went to Drupal conferences, all the Drupal devs were totally
lovely people and really made me want to contribute to Drupal)</li>
</ul>

<p>For competence, I&rsquo;ll ask:</p>

<p><strong>Is there anything that will stop me from getting work done?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Do I know the language this is written in? Is it easy to learn?</li>
<li>Can I set up a dev environment easily on my computer?</li>
<li>How complex is the codebase? Is it approachable? Is the
documentation good?</li>
<li>If I don&rsquo;t know something I need to know, will the community answer
my questions? Will they be jerks? Is the mailing list active?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="why-i-don-t">why I don&rsquo;t</h2>

<p>I usually don&rsquo;t contribute to open source because of <em>relatedness</em> &ndash;
I don&rsquo;t know what I&rsquo;ll get out of it! A super great example of this is
Drupal. <a href="https://drupal.org/">Drupal</a> is a tremendously important
project. I&rsquo;ve contributed to it before! I could do it again! The
community is extraordinarily welcoming! But it&rsquo;s missing <em>relatedness</em>
for me right now &ndash; I&rsquo;m not developing websites anymore.</p>

<p>Most open source projects fails relatedness &ndash; if I don&rsquo;t use it,
don&rsquo;t want to learn about it right now, don&rsquo;t know anyone who works on
it, and/or don&rsquo;t believe strongly in its mission, I probably don&rsquo;t
want to contribute! This is TOTALLY OKAY. There are tons of people who
are contributing to those projects! They will be okay without me =)</p>

<p>A great example of a project that fails competence is Pidgin, above &ndash;
I might have had some issue with my chat client that I wanted to fix,
but the barrier to entry seemed too high at the time.</p>

<h2 id="why-i-do">why I do!</h2>

<p>Here are some open source-y projects I have worked on and why:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ipython/ipython">IPython</a>, because there was a
feature I wanted it to have that it didn&rsquo;t! Now it does! One of my
PRs got merged into IPython and it is SUPER COOL.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://github.com/jvns/pandas-cookbook">pandas cookbook</a>,
because when I learned pandas there weren&rsquo;t as many practical
materials as I wanted! Now there&rsquo;s one more! People are learning
more about pandas because I wrote a thing! THE BEST.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jvns/gzip.jl">gzip in julia</a>, to learn how gzip
worked. Now I know! AWESOME.</li>
</ul>

<p>Working on open source projects can be super fun! Yay!</p>

<h2 id="don-t-feel-guilty">don&rsquo;t feel guilty</h2>

<p>There are so many things you could be doing. If it takes 30 hours of
your time over 3 weeks to fix a network card issue, maybe that&rsquo;s
worthwhile because you learned a lot and your hardware works better!
Or maybe you would rather spend that time with your family or friends
or volunteering or playing soccer or watching movies or working to pay
your rent.</p>

<p>I sometimes hear people say &ldquo;you should write open source software!&rdquo;
like it&rsquo;s a universal good. Don&rsquo;t. Do it if it makes sense for you! Do
it if you know what you&rsquo;ll get out of it, and you feel that it&rsquo;s worth
your time! If not, do other things instead!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 8: Julia writes Julia! And remembers that open source is hard.]]></title>
    <link href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/10/12/day-8-julia-writes-julia-and-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://jvns.ca/blog/2013/10/12/day-8-julia-writes-julia-and-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Hacker School this batch there is a wonderful thing called the
<a href="https://www.hackerschool.com/blog/23-announcing-the-hacker-school-maintainers-program">maintainers program</a>.
This means that lovely open source project maintainers come help Hacker
Schoolers contribute to their projects!</p>

<p>Yesterday <a href="http://karpinski.org/">Stefan Karpinski</a> came to talk about
<a href="http://julialang.org">Julia</a>. Some reasons I&rsquo;m excited about working on
Julia:</p>

<ul>
<li>The potential for &ldquo;Julia works on Julia in Julia&rdquo;</li>
<li>Much of the code for Julia is written in Julia, unlike in Python where
if you want to write fast code you have to write it in C. This seems
pretty huge to me.</li>
<li>The community seems really nice</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m into scientific computing &amp; data science, and that&rsquo;s what it&rsquo;s for</li>
<li>There&rsquo;s a <a href="http://juliastats.github.com/DataFrames.jl">DataFrames</a>
library for Julia, which I&rsquo;ve already contributed a tiny bit to!</li>
<li>I love the IPython Notebook to death, and Julia has a backend for it
so that there&rsquo;s an IJulia Notebook! &lt;3 &lt;3 &lt;3
</li>
</ul>

<p>However:</p>

<p>The thing I forgot about open source is that open source (for me!) is
<em>scary</em> and <em>hard</em>.  Discussing bugs on mailing lists and issue trackers
and submitting pull requests is <em>terrifying</em>. I have gone to awesome
code sprints with really lovely supportive people and gone home and
cried because being new to a project and trying to get work done is
sometimes <em>so frustrating</em>. Like you can spend 12 hours trying to fix a
tiny bug and get <em>nowhere</em>. And say ALL OF THE THINGS THAT ARE CONFUSED
AND WRONG. IN PUBLIC.</p>

<p>HOWEVER!</p>

<p>This is <em>why I&rsquo;m at Hacker School</em>. And I&rsquo;m going to work on lots of
open source anyway and write code and make pull requests and then it
will not be terrifying. I think Julia is a pretty good place to do this.
And pairing with people makes doing this stuff way easier.</p>

<p>AND I MADE PULL REQUESTS TODAY.
<a href="https://github.com/JuliaStats/DataFrames.jl/commits?author=jvns">merged</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/JuliaStats/DataFrames.jl/pull/376#issuecomment-26179926">not merged yet</a>.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>